{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "In preparation for this event, the Octagon House was converted into a French consulate for its protection; it was later converted into federal housing. This event, a response to the destruction of private homes during the Raid on Port Dover, was preceded by the Battle of Bladensburg and ended in part by a fluke tornado. This event caused an evacuation of a copy of the Lansdowne Portrait, which was legendarily saved by Dolley Madison. For ten points, name this 1814 event in which British forces torched the capital of the United States.",
      "answer": [
        "burning of Washington D.C.",
        "equivalents"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Five deities were born from this goddess’s necklace of 500 jewels. To lure this deity out of hiding, a dawn goddess performed a strip tease on top of an overturned tub. This goddess’s brother threw a flayed horse into a room containing her weavers, causing her to retreat into a cave in anger. This goddess, who was born when her father Izanagi washed his left eye, is worshiped at the Ise [ee-say] Shrine. The Emperor of Japan descended from, for ten points, what sun goddess of Shinto myth?",
      "answer": "Amaterasu"
    },
    {
      "question": "Radio host Alan Berg was murdered by a group advocating this belief known as the Order. Executions occur during the “Day of the Rope” in a book that furthers this belief, written by William Luther Pierce; that book is The Turner Diaries, pages of which were found in the car of Timothy McVeigh upon his arrest. The website Stormfront was founded by a former Grand Wizard of the Ku Klux Klan to promote, for ten points, what racial ideology promoted by groups like Aryan Nations?",
      "answer": [
        "white supremacism",
        "white nationalism",
        "word forms"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The largest civilian effort of this type used an area codenamed “Annabelle” in the city of Uli, but hostile forces using the call sign “Genocide” attempted to thwart that church-supported effort during the Biafran War. Another event of this type was coordinated by men like Curtis LeMay and Lucius Clay and codenamed Operation Vittles by the Americans; that 1948 to 1949 effort saw over 8,000 tons of food and supplies provided each day. For ten points, name this type of supply effort carried out over a Soviet blockade in Cold War Berlin.",
      "answer": [
        "airlifts",
        "Berlin Airlift",
        "Biafran Airlift"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A former leader of this party was defeated in a 2017 election by Colin Clark. The 79 Group was a left wing faction of this party, whose supporters are divided into gradualist and fundamentalist wings. Winnie Ewing won the Hamilton riding in a 1967 by-election, this party’s second-ever seat in Parliament. Nicola Sturgeon became the leader of this party after Alex Salmond resigned due to the failure of a 2014 independence referendum. For ten points, name this third largest political party in the British House of Commons, a prominent advocate for the independence of Scotland.",
      "answer": "Scottish National Party"
    },
    {
      "question": "Frederick II legitimized this group’s land holdings in the Golden Bull of Rimini. This organization was summoned by Duke Konrad I to defend his territory against the Old Prussians, who they ended up conquering. This group’s incursion into Russia was beaten back at the Battle on the Ice by Alexander Nevsky, and another of their military losses came against the Kingdom of Poland and the Grand Duchy of Lithuania at the Battle of Grunwald. For ten points, name this Catholic military order.",
      "answer": [
        "Teutonic Knights or the Teutonic Order",
        "Order of Brothers of the German House of Saint Mary in Jerusalem"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "A commander from this state lost his right arm at the Battle of Fair Oaks and commanded the XI Corps [“eleventh core”], who were decisively outflanked at the Battle of Chancellorsville. Union general O.O. Howard hailed from this state, as did the Vice President during much of the Civil War, Hannibal Hamlin. Joshua Chamberlain commanded this state’s 20th Volunteer Regiment, which defended Little Round Top during the Battle of Gettysburg. For ten points, name this state where regiments were mustered near Portland.",
      "answer": "Maine"
    },
    {
      "question": "A poem criticizing British involvement in these conflicts ruined Anna Barbault’s public reputation and career. The lines “The boy stood on the burning deck / Whence all but he had fled” open a Felicia Hemans poem inspired by one of these conflicts titled “Casabianca.” A novel that fictionalizes these conflicts includes a chapter set at the Duchess of Richmond’s ball in Brussels, after which George Osborne is killed at Quatre Bras. For ten points, name this set of conflicts that provides the backdrop of Vanity Fair, in which several men survive the Battle of Waterloo.",
      "answer": "Napoleonic Wars"
    },
    {
      "question": "This ruler’s government was challenged by the Green March. The Vertical Syndicate was the only labor union allowed in this ruler’s country. The Valley of the Fallen was commissioned by this man as a symbol of reconciliation. This ruler’s prime minister was killed in Operation Ogre by Basque separatists. The death of Jos´e Sanjurjo helped propel this man to power. The Carlists and Falange were merged by, for ten points, what longtime dictator of Spain?",
      "answer": "Francisco Franco Bahamonde"
    },
    {
      "question": "Excavation efforts by Hormuzd Rassam located the contents of these buildings in the temple of Samas in Sippar. Another of these buildings housed two huge statues of Dagon and two rooms called “houses of the rolls;” that building of this type was allegedly visited by Alexander the Great. A palace in Nineveh was home to one of these buildings built by Ashurbanipal that contained thousands of cuneiform tablets. For ten points, name this type of location where the Epic of Gilgamesh and other literary works may have been stored.",
      "answer": "Mesopotamian library"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This work and a work accusing Samuel Chase of using insider knowledge to corner the flour market were published under the same name. The New York Packet published a section of this work that argues for paying the President an ample salary, thereby avoiding the temptation for corruption. Another section ofthisworkclaimsthataBillofRightswouldbedangerousandunnecessary;thatsectionisthe84thentry in this work. For ten points, name this series of essays that promote and defend the U.S. Constitution, written by Hamilton, Jay, and Madison.",
        "answer": "The Federalist Papers"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Federalist Papers were written by Jay, Hamilton, and Madison under this pseudonym.",
        "answer": "Publius"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Winston Churchill criticized this man’s government for “[frolicing] [...] to their heart’s content” with the Germans and Japanese shortly after this man controversially offered formal condolences to the German embassy after the death of Hitler. This politician remarked “they are our people, and their sorrows are our sorrows” after a neighboring country was attacked in the Belfast Blitz. Fianna Fail [fe-enna foil] was founded by, for ten points, what politician, the first Taoiseach [tee-shuh] of Ireland?",
        "answer": "Eamon de Valera or Edward de Valera"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Eamon de Valera was a colleague, then a rival, of this Irish independence fighter who was assassinated in a 1922 ambush in County Cork.",
        "answer": "Michael Collins"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In a Raphael portrait, one of these leaders appears lost in thought with a long white beard. A series of paintings showing these leaders with disfigured faces was created by Francis Bacon. A portrait of Felice, the illegitimate daughter of one of these leaders, appears in the Apostolic Palace. Diego Vel´azquez painted one of these men from the Pamphili family wearing glasses, Innocent X. For ten points, name these prominent patrons and subjects of art who head the Catholic Church.",
        "answer": "Pope"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "One of the most prolific art patron popes was this della Rovere pope, who was painted by Raphael and commissioned the ceiling frescoes of the Sistine Chapel.",
        "answer": "Julius II"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "After this dynasty’s Emperor Taiding died, it suffered the War of the Two Capitals. This dynasty, which gained power after winning the Battle of Yamen, built its capital at Dadu. The Red Turban Revolt, which included the future Hongwu emperor, successfully overthrew this dynasty. The founder of this dynasty had previously won the Toluid Civil War after Mongke Khan died. Marco Polo recorded visiting, for ten points, what Mongol Chinese dynasty that preceded the Ming?",
        "answer": "Yuan Dynasty"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The 1279 Battle of Yamen was decisive in ending this dynasty’s rule of China.",
        "answer": "Southern Song Dynasty"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The local name of this discovery is “Dinkinesh,” which translates to “You are marvelous” in Amharic. Twenty years after this discovery was made, it was improved upon by Ardi, also found in the Awash River valley. A valgus knee and aspects of a conical rib cage were found as part of this discovery, indicating a plant-based diet and upright walking motion. This discovery consists of a few hundred fragments of bone, roughly 40 percent of a female Australopithecus skeleton. For ten points, name this collection of hominid fossils discovered in Ethiopia in 1974, named for the Beatles song playing in the excavators’ camp.",
        "answer": "Lucy"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Lucy is a member of the genus Australopithecus and this species, named for the region of northern Ethiopia where she was found.",
        "answer": "Afarensis"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A man with this surname supervised the construction of a fort at Prospect Bluff on the orders of Andrew Jackson. Another man with this surname led a group of militia who constructed a bridge to escape from Sullivan’s Island during the defense of Fort Moultrie. A former executive of the South Carolina Railroad Company with this surname was authorized to acquire a strip of land that contains present-day Tucson. For ten points, give this surname shared by the man who negotiated a $10 million purchase of land from Mexico.",
        "answer": [
          "Gadsden",
          "James Gadsden",
          "Christopher Gadsden after “militia” is read"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During the American Revolution, Christopher Gadsden designed an iconic yellow flag featuring an animal and a four-word slogan. Either name the animal or give the slogan.",
        "answer": [
          "rattlesnake",
          "Don’t Tread on Me"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A ruler in this modern-day nation sided with Naples in the Treaty of Gaeta and formed the League of Lezh¨e. Ismail Qemali [ish-mail kem-ah-lee] helped this nation gain independence at the Assembly of Vlor¨e [v’lor-uh]. In the 15th century, a historical region that became this nation fought off the Ottomans with the help of Skanderbeg. For ten points, name this Balkan nation that Enver Hoxha [hoh-cha] governed from its capital, Tirana.",
        "answer": "Albania"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 1939, Italy deposed this Albanian leader, who had been made King in 1928.",
        "answer": [
          "Zog I",
          "Ahmet Muhtar Zogolli",
          "Ahmet Zogu"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In this country in 2016, referee C´esar Flores was shot and killed on the pitch by a player he’d sent off. A soccer club in this country plays home games in the La Bombonera; that team is the Boca Juniors. During a heated game in the 1986 World Cup, a midfielder who played for this country scored the “Hand of God” goal, shortly followed by the “Goal of the Century.” For ten points, name this country that lost the most recent World Cup Final to Germany and whose current roster includes Lionel Messi.",
        "answer": "Argentina"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This midfield striker scored the “Hand of God” and “Goal of the Century,” and was ejected from the 1994 World Cup for failing a doping test. In 2005, he protested George W. Bush by wearing a shirt replacing the “s” in Bush’s name with a swastika.",
        "answer": "Diego Maradona"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Spanish-American War",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Pacific country that George Dewey invaded at Manila Bay.",
          "answer": "The Philippines"
        },
        {
          "question": "Volunteer cavalry battalion led by Teddy Roosevelt during the Battle of San Juan Hill.",
          "answer": "Rough Riders or 1st US Volunteer Cavalry"
        },
        {
          "question": "Warship whose mysterious sinking in Havana harbor sparked a popular slogan.",
          "answer": "USS Maine"
        },
        {
          "question": "Future Secretary of State who described the affair as a “splendid little war.”",
          "answer": "John Hay"
        },
        {
          "question": "1901 legislation that allowed the U.S. to control Cuba’s foreign relations.",
          "answer": "Platt Amendment"
        },
        {
          "question": "Earlier legislation that prevented the U.S. from annexing Cuba during the war.",
          "answer": "Teller Amendment"
        },
        {
          "question": "Spanish general known as the “Butcher” who brutally suppressed the 1895 Cuban revolt.",
          "answer": "Don Valeriano “Butcher” Weyler y Nicolau"
        },
        {
          "question": "Letter, written by the Spanish Ambassador to the U.S., that called McKinley weak and pushed the American public to war.",
          "answer": "Don Enrique Dupuy de Lˆome’s letter"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Collaborationist France",
      "prompt": "In France under Nazi Germany, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Leader of the non-collaborationist Free French forces.",
          "answer": "Charles de Gaulle"
        },
        {
          "question": "City that names the successor to the Third Republic.",
          "answer": "Vichy France"
        },
        {
          "question": "World War I hero who initially led that puppet state.",
          "answer": "Henri Phillipe P´etain"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nazi secret police, created by Goering, that helped repress France.",
          "answer": [
            "Gestapo",
            "Geheime Staatspolizei"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Country that attacked the French fleet at Mers-el-K´ebir in July 1940.",
          "answer": [
            "United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland",
            "England",
            "Great Britain"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Allied invasion of North Africa that was opposed by collaborationist French forces.",
          "answer": "Operation Torch"
        },
        {
          "question": "Second Prime Minister of collaborationist France, who was later executed for high treason.",
          "answer": "Pierre Laval"
        },
        {
          "question": "Mass arrest of Parisian Jews on the 16 and 17 July 1942, who were held at the namesake sports center.",
          "answer": [
            "Vel d’Hiv Roundup",
            "V´elodrome d’Hiver"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Meiji Restoration",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Capital city of the Tokugawa Shogunate; it was renamed after the Restoration. Give either name.",
          "answer": [
            "Edo",
            "Tokyo"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Social class of Japanese warriors that was gradually abolished after the Restoration.",
          "answer": "samurai"
        },
        {
          "question": "American naval officer whose arrival in 1854 provided the impetus for the Meiji Restoration.",
          "answer": "Matthew Perry"
        },
        {
          "question": "Island north of Honshu where shogunate loyalists established the Republic of Ezo.",
          "answer": "Hokkaido"
        },
        {
          "question": "First constitution of modern Japan, promulgated at the enthronement of the Emperor Meiji.",
          "answer": "Charter Oath or Gokajo no Goseimon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Short civil war in which pro-imperial forces won the Battle of Toba-Fushimi against pro-Shogunate forces.",
          "answer": "Boshin War"
        },
        {
          "question": "Last Tokugawa shogun of Japan.",
          "answer": "Tokugawa Yoshinobu"
        },
        {
          "question": "Domain that, with the Choshu domain, led pro-Imperial forces. Saigo Takimori was a member of this domain.",
          "answer": "Satsuma Domain"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This city was saved from destruction following a loss at Cape Ecnomus thanks to the arrival of the Spartan mercenary Xanthippus [zan-thi-puss]. This city was able to retain its Libyan settlements after putting down a revolt in the (20 pts)",
        "Truceless War. A commander from this city had his head thrown into his brother’s tent following the Battle of the Metaurus. The (10 pts)",
        "Fabian strategy of delay was used against this city, which met its final defeat when loud horns thwarted its contingent of elephants at the battle of Zama. For ten points, name this city that fought three Punic Wars with Rome."
      ],
      "answer": "Carthage"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country’s Foreign Minister Mariano Baptista signed an 1874 treaty settling its western border, but this country reneged on the agreement a year later. This country solidified control of its southern valley of Tarija in exchange for giving up control of the (20 pts)",
        "Atacama Plateau. The Lacajahuira [lah-kah-h’weera] River is the only drainage of this country’s Lake Poop´o [poh-poh]. The remains of (10 pts)",
        "Tiwanaku were discovered in this country near the southeastern shores of Lake Titicaca. For ten points, name this South American country whose constitutional capital is named for Antonio Jos´e de Sucre [soo-kray]."
      ],
      "answer": "Bolivia"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Opponents of this man argued that his politics had been influenced by his affair with Jean Tatlock. This man, whose loyalty was questioned by the Borden Letter, was approached by a literature professor with (20 pts)",
        "Soviet ties in the Chevalier Incident. This man’s Q-Clearance was revoked just one day before it was to expire as the result of a (10 pts)",
        "1954 security hearing. Accusations of communist sympathies tarnished the reputation of, for ten points, what scientist who directed the Los Alamos Laboratory as part of the Manhattan Project?"
      ],
      "answer": "J. Robert Oppenheimer"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man stated “Gold is a relic of Julius Caesar, and interest is an invention of Satan” while advocating for monetary reform. After the death of his wife, this man moved to West Orange where he built the Glenmont estate. This man founded a (20 pts)",
        "film studio on the back of his kinetograph, which allowed him to make The Great Train Robbery. George (10 pts)",
        "Westinghouse feuded with this man, who participated in the “War of the Currents” against his former employee, Nikola Tesla. Menlo Park was the home of, for ten points, what inventor commonly attributed with creating the light bulb?"
      ],
      "answer": "Thomas Edison"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This battle enabled Marco Barbaro to broker a peace that would not be broken until the War of Candia. The Knights of Saint Stephen legendarily captured the enemy standards during a counterattack by Marcantonio Colonna in this battle. One side found time to gather its forces for this battle after (20 pts)",
        "Marco Bragadin’s last stand at Famagusta. The flagship Real [ray-ahl] withstood an attack by Ulu¸c Ali [oo-looch Ali] in this battle, where (10 pts)",
        "Miguel Cervantes lost his left arm. For ten points, name this 1571 battle in which Don Juan of Austria’s Holy League defeated an Ottoman fleet."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Lepanto"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A type of song performed in this country during Holy Week takes its name from the Latin for “dart.” A composer depicted this country with a twelve-movement piano suite that depicts a saeta in its third movement and opens with (20 pts)",
        "“Evocacaion.” [evo-CASS-ee-ohn]. Another composer from this country was inspired by the royal gardens of Philip II to write a guitar concerto, (10 pts)",
        "Concierto de Aranjuez [con-see-air-toh de ar-an-WETH], whose middle movement was supposedly inspired by the bombing of Guernica. Isaac Albeniz and Joaquin Rodrigo were from, for ten points, what country whose region of Andalusia is home to flamenco music?"
      ],
      "answer": "Spain"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The priest Francisco Romero demanded that people produce this commodity as penance. This commodity is cultivated in a namesake “triangle” in the Paisa region. This commodity was produced in the Paraiba Valley in a boom starting in the 1890s, where it was shipped from (20 pts)",
        "Santos. This commodity’s production in the province of Sao Paulo, as opposed to Minas Gerais’ [mee-nas zhe-RISE] production of (10 pts)",
        "dairy, provides the nickname of this commodity “with milk” to a period of Brazilian history. For ten points, name this caffeinated beverage."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "coffee",
        "coffee beans and other related answers"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) After one of these specific events, Mary Peckham became concerned after her neighbor’s door was found to be locked. Reverend George Kelly was a suspect in one of these events at Villisca, Iowa. One of these incidents in New Orleans involved a letter that claimed if jazz music were played, (20 pts)",
        "lives would be spared. One of these events was followed by testimony from the maid Bridget Sullivan in New Bedford, Massachusetts. U.S. Army officers Arthur Bonifas and Mark Barrett were the victims in another of these events that motivated Operation (10 pts)",
        "Paul Bunyan. Lizzie Borden was implicated in, for ten points, what type of event in which she “gave her father forty-one” whacks?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "axe murders",
        "descriptive answer of killing people with an axe"
      ]
    }
  ]
}